Pete Welding collection, 1958-1995
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Pete Welding collection 1958-1995 1961-1980
AFC 2011/053
Welding, Pete, collector
approximately 7873 items
5091 sheets (16.25 linear feet)
832 sound tape reels; various sizes
760 photographic prints and contact sheets: black and white; various sizes
1066 negatives: black-and-white original negatives and copy negatives
111 photographs: color transparencies; 120 mm (slide format)
2 photographs: color transparencies; 120 mm (slide format, unmounted)
6 photographs: color film negatives; 35 mm (roll format)
2 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format)
3 drawings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of over eight hundred sound tape reels, including blues and jazz music and interviews with musicians; several hundred photographs of prominent blues and jazz musicians, primarily from the 1960s and 1970s; manuscript materials about blues and jazz musicians, arranged by the name of performer; and articles, drafts, and notes written by Pete Welding, journalist, record producer, and historian of blues music.
Provenance
Darlene Welding, purchase; 2011.
Related Material
Alan Lomax, Zora Neale Hurston, and Mary Elizabeth Barnicle expedition collection (AFC 1935/001)
John Lomax Southern States Collection, 1933-1937 (AFC 1935/002)
Alan and Elizabeth Lomax Kentucky Collection (AFC 1937/001)
John A. Lomax and Alton C. Morris Florida Collection, 1937 (AFC 1937/004)
John A. Lomax Southern States collection, 1937 (AFC 1937/007)
John and Ruby Lomax 1939 Southern States Trip (AFC 1939/001)
Herbert Halpert 1939 Southern States recording expedition (AFC 1939/005)
Resettlement Administration recordings collection (AFC 1939/016)
Library of Congress and Fisk University Mississippi Delta collection, 1941-1943 (AFC 1941/002)
Alan Lomax recordings from Saltville, Virginia (AFC 1943/005)
Darlene Welding, Larry Cohn, and Bruce Bromberg oral history interview (AFC 2010/020)
Bruce Jackson and Diane Christian collection (AFC 2011/009)
Tom Hoskins collection, 1963-1967 (AFC 2011/026)
Access and Restrictions
The Pete Welding collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Pete Welding (1935-1995), an authority on blues and jazz music, worked as a writer and music producer, and was a life-long advocate for traditional blues and avant-garde jazz performers. He wrote regularly for Down Beat magazine, wrote liner notes for albums (including releases by Frank Sinatra, Memphis Slim, Nat King Cole, Ian & Sylvia, and the Paul Butterfield Blues Band), and edited books on jazz and blues music. His research for his writings involved interviews of notable figures across music genres, including Signifyin' Mary Johnson, John Lee Hooker, Pete Robinson, Howlin' Wolf, Judy Collins, Thomas A. Dorsey, and others. He founded Testament Records in 1963 as a platform for African American folk, blues, and gospel performers, and produced records by Quicksilver Messenger Service, Big Joe Williams, and Jean-Luc Ponty, to name a few. Twice nominated for a Grammy Award (1973 and 1993), he was posthumously inducted into the Blues Hall of Fame (1996) in the category known (at that time) as Business-Production: Media or Academic. His works continue to be widely-cited resources for music researchers.
Scope and Content
Collection of over eight hundred sound tape reels, including blues and jazz music and interviews with musicians; several hundred photographs of prominent blues and jazz musicians, primarily from the 1960s and 1970s; manuscript materials about blues and jazz musicians, arranged by the name of performer; and articles, drafts, and notes written by Pete Welding, journalist, record producer, and historian of blues music.
Arrangement
The Pete Welding collection is organized in 10 series:
Series 1: Writings about performers
Series 2: Typed drafts of Blues Book and Jazz Book, by Pete Welding
Series 3: Testament Records
Series 4: Articles, reviews, and other writings
Series 5: Publications
Series 6: Materials from sound recording containers, and original containers
Series 7: Oversized materials
Series 8: Sound recordings
Series 9: Photographic materials
Series 10: Sketches
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Collins, Judy, 1939-; House, Son; Howlin' Wolf, 1910-1976; Kramer, Marshall Howard; McCoy, Ethel; McCoy, George, -1988; McCoy, Ruby; Muddy Waters, 1915-1983; Welding, Pete; Williams, Big Joe, 1903-1982
Organizations
Blue Sky Boys; Contraband (Jazz group); Dolenz, Jones, Boyce & Hart (Musical group)
Subjects
African American musicians.; Blues (Music); Blues musicians.; Jazz festivals--Illinois--Chicago.; Jazz festivals--Japan.; Jazz festivals--Switzerland--Montreux.; Jazz musicians.
Form/Genre
Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Writings about performers
  - Ammons and Johnson, July 1937 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Transcript of an article by Sharon A. Pease published in Down Beat, July 1937.
  - Billy Boy Arnold, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
    Typed interview transcript.
  - Kokomo Arnold, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
    Original pages from a published article.
  - Danny Barker, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
    "The Pine-Scented Sovereign State of Miss'sippi," an essay by Danny Barker. Original issue of For Now, issue #2, pages 25-38.
  - Otis Blackwell, February 18, 1971 (Box-folder 1/6)
    "In the Beginning There Was O.," by Peter McCabe. Original pages from Rolling Stone.
  - Scrapper Blackwell, October 11, 1962 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Original newspaper clipping.
  - Bobby Bland, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
    Three original magazine clippings.
  - Big Bill Broonzy, February 14, 1970 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Original clipping from a magazine, plus a copy of the page proofs.
  - Elijah Brown, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    Typed draft of an article, with handwritten edits.
  - James Brown, October 31, 1968, March 6, 1971 (Box-folder 1/11)
    Two published articles.
  - Frank Butler, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    Typed interview transcript and writings, with handwritten edits.
  - Canned Heat, undated (Box-folders 1/13-14)
    Typed interview transcripts, with handwritten edits, published articles (original pages from publications), and drafts of a published article.
  - Hoagy Carmichael, undated (Box-folder 1/15)
    Typed draft of an article, with corrections.
  - Leroy Carr, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
    Photocopy from a magazine.
  - Clifton Chenier, September-October 1975 (Box-folder 1/17)
    Original clipping from a magazine.
  - June Christy, undated (Box-folder 1/18)
    Handwritten and typed writings, as well as a newspaper clipping and photocopied pages from various publications.
  - Nat King Cole, undated (Box-folder 1/19)
    Photocopied CD liner notes, typed and handwritten notes, photocopied pages from publications, and typed drafts of writings. Also includes a published copy of Nat "King" Cole: The Capitol Years (which would have accompanied a boxed set of recordings).
  - Albert Collins, undated (Box-folder 1/20)
    Typed draft of an article, and hand-drawn portraits on lined paper. See box-folder 20/1 for oversized materials.
  - Contraband, undated (Box-folder 1/21)
    Photocopy of a published review.
  - Elizabeth Cotten, March 1975 (Box-folder 1/22)
    "Elizabeth Cotten, Folk Guitar Legend," by Jon Monday. Published in Guitar Player, vol. 9, no. 3.
  - David Crittendon and Barbara White, 1978 (Box-folder 1/23)
    Handwritten note from David Crittendon to Pete Welding, on yellow legal paper, and typed lyrics by Crittendon and White, and photocopies of the music to which the lyrics were set.
  - Big Boy Crudup, June 19, 1971; undated (Box-folder 1/24)
    Two published articles; one original and one photocopied.
  - Teddy Darby, undated (Box-folder 1/25)
    Handwritten note from Ted Darby to Pete Welding, dated April 15, 1965; and a typed interview transcript with handwritten edits and notes. A photo has been relocated to box-folder 21/12.
  - Blind Gary Davis, August 1965 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Bo Diddley, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
    Photocopy of a published article plus a one-page typed song list.
  - Willie Dixon, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
    Photocopy of a typed letter from Pete Welding to "Bill," typed writings with handwritten edits, and published writings (original and photocopies).
  - Thomas A. Dorsey, undated (Box-folder 2/3)
    Two published writings (one original, one photocopy), and typed sections of a book draft.
  - Jack Dupree, January 1960 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Photocopy of a published article.
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards, April 26, 1968; undated (Box-folder 2/5)
    Original typed letter, (signed) from Rae Korson to Pete Welding; typed list of recordings of Edwards by Alan Lomax, and typed draft of an interview with or article about Edwards.
  - Sleep John Estes, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Press release from Delmark Records, proof and final copies of a published article, and a published news article.
  - Jesse Fuller, February 1964 (Box-folder 2/7)
    Original pages from BMI News.
  - Lowell Fulson, 1976-1977; undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    Typed drafts, one with handwritten edits, original pages from a published article, and a photocopied album review.
  - Jazz Gillum, 1966-1978 (Box-folder 2/9)
    Photocopied and original articles, and other published materials.
  - John Lee Granderson, 1967; undated (Box-folder 2/10)
    Handwritten and typed items of correspondence from John Lee Granderson to Pete Welding, and a brief typed autobiography.
  - Buddy Guy, 1968; undated (Box-folder 2/11)
    Typed draft of a published article, and two published articles (one original and one photocopy).
  - Coleman Hawkins, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    Typed draft of album liner notes, with handwritten edits.
  - John Lee Henley, undated (Box-folder 2/13)
    Typed draft of a "bio-discography," with handwritten edits.
  - Smokey Hogg, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
    Typed drafts of a published article (two copies with handwritten notes), and a selected discography.
  - Earl Hooker, May 9, 1970 (Box-folder 2/15)
    Original magazine article.
  - John Lee Hooker, 1964-1977 (Box-folder 2/16)
    Original copies of published articles, typed drafts of album liner notes and a brief published article.
  - Sam "Lightnin'" Hopkins, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 2/17)
    Original copies of published articles, and correspondence from various individuals. A photo has been relocated to box-folder 21/25.
  - Son House; 1964-1971, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
    Empty envelope from John D. Carney (Son House's brother-in-law), original published articles, a promotional flyer, and a typed partial transcript of an interview.
  - Bee Houston, July 1975 (Box-folder 3/2)
    "Bee Houston," by Eric Kirss. Original pages from Guitar Player, vol. 9, no. 7.
  - Peg Leg Howell, 1963; undated (Box-folder 3/3)
    Typed drafts of writings, including an interview transcript, a handwritten tape log, typed discographies, handwritten notes, correspondence, and a mock-up of "The Man and His Blues," by George Mitchell. The mock-up includes two original photos affixed to a page.
  - Howlin' Wolf, 1967-1977; undated (Box-folder 3/4)
    Original pages from published articles, one photocopied article, a typed draft of a published interview, with handwritten edits, and typed drafts of album liner notes.
  - Mississippi John Hurt, April-May 1965 (Box-folder 3/5)
    Photocopied pages from an interview by Patrick Watson published in code [sic].
  - Mahalia Jackson, January 1965; undated (Box-folder 3/6)
    Typed draft of album liner notes, a typed draft of an interview, and original pages from an article published in Music Journal.
  - Elmore James, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    Typed draft of liner notes.
  - Lil' Son Johnson, March 15, 1995; undated (Box-folder 3/8)
    Handwritten notes, photocopies of information published in various sources, discographies, typed drafts of short biographies, typed minutes from the Blues Task Force meeting (March 15, 1995), and other typed drafts of published writings.
  - Lonnie Johnson, 1939-1982; undated (Box-folder 3/9)
    Original clippings from publications, a typed draft of album liner notes, a published offprint, and a typed copy of part of a published article.
  - Pete Johnson, 1967; undated (Box-folder 3/10)
    Original clipping and a page from publications, a typed copy of part of a published article, and a draft of information to accompany a published article. Two photos were relocated to box-folder 21/36.
  - Robert Johnson, 1969-1991; undated (Box-folders 3/11-13)
    Published materials (original and photocopies), correspondence, a copy of Blues World, no.1, photocopied job sheets, typed drafts of published articles, typed draft of album liner notes, typed lyrics, handwritten notes, and a typed copy of part of an interview with Son House (where he discussed Robert Johnson).
  - Curtis Jones, 1964; 1966 (Box-folder 4/1)
    Original copies of two published articles.
  - Scott Joplin, November 25, 1971 (Box-folder 4/2)
    "Scott Joplin: Genius Rediscovered," by Martin Williams. Published pages from Down Beat.
  - "K," 1966-1968 (Box-folder 4/3)
    Items of correspondence.
  - Stan Kenton, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    Handwritten notes, a typed list of performances, typed drafts of a published article, with handwritten edits.
  - Stan Kenton - "Collectors" CD proposal; 1989-1992, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    Correspondence, typed drafts, typed discographies, and typed draft of liner notes.
  - Albert King, 1976, 1978. (Box-folder 4/6)
    Original pages from three published articles.
  - B.B. King, 1967-1982 (Box-folders 4/7-8)
    Original pages from published articles, typed drafts (including liner notes with handwritten corrections), handwritten notes, correspondence, typed cut list for a proposed album, and related documents.
  - Freddie King; 1971-1977, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
    Original and photocopied pages from published articles.
  - "L," 1966; undated (Box-folder 4/10)
    Typed and handwritten correspondence.
  - Leadbelly; 1966-1970, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Peggy Lee; 1995, undated (Box-folder 4/12)
    Correspondence, photocopy of a published article, typed session information on index cards, label copy and notice of copy documents, and related materials.
  - Meade Lux Lewis, undated (Box-folder 4/13)
    Typed draft of an article on Lewis, by Sharon A. Pease.
  - Mance Lipscomb, 1962-1976 (Box-folder 4/14)
    Two typed drafts of an interview, original pages from published articles, and a photocopy of a newspaper article.
  - Little Walter, 1968, undated (Box-folder 4/15)
    Photocopied list of Little Walter unreleased recordings for duplication, typed information to be included in liner notes, a song title list, a typed draft of liner notes, a typed draft of other notes, and original pages from an article published in Down Beat.
  - Robert Lockwood, Jr., November 1975 (Box-folder 4/16)
    "Robert Lockwood, Jr.: Master of the Blues," by Mit Schuller. Original pages from an article published in Guitar Player ., vol. 9, no. 11.
  - Bill McAdoo, 1961 (Box-folder 5/1)
    Saturday Review (complete issue - April 29, 1961), which includes an article by Pete Welding, typed autobiographical notes, and correspondence.
  - Fred McDowell; 1966, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
    Typed draft of interview transcript, with handwritten edits, typed draft of a published article, and original pages from a published article.
  - Brownie McGhee; 1958-1973, undated (Box-folder 5/3)
    Pages from published articles (original and photocopies), and "Sonny Terry and Brownie McGhee Press Book: 1959-1960 Tour of India" (typed document), by Paul Endicott.
  - Magic Sam, August 7, 1969 (Box-folder 5/4)
    "West Side Soul: Magic Sam," by Michael Cuscuna. One-page photocopy of article from Down Beat.
  - Taj Mahal; 1971, undated (Box-folder 5/5)
    Original pages from published articles.
  - Carl Martin, undated (Box-folder 5/6)
    Typed discography, typed draft of a published article, and typed transcript of an interview.
  - Frank Melrose, May 1945 (Box-folder 5/7)
    Jazz Record, no. 32. Includes "Barrelhouse Frank Melrose," by Pete Daley.
  - Memphis Slim, 1960, 1970 (Box-folder 5/8)
    Pages from published articles (one original, one photocopy).
  - Big Maceo Merriweather, undated (Box-folder 5/9)
    "Big Maceo," by Paul Oliver (photocopy of a published article.
  - Elmon Mickle, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
    Typed draft of a paper, with handwritten edits.
  - Amos Milburn, September 1995 (Box-folder 5/11)
    Typed copy of a published article.
  - Gloria Oden, 1978-1989 (Box-folder 5/12)
    Reprint of a published interview, correspondence, a photocopy of a published paper, typed and signed document by Gloria Oden, a photocopy of a published article, and Gloria Oden's curriculum vitae.
  - Johnny Otis; 1970-1980, undated (Box-folders 5/13-15)
    Typed draft of an autobiographical document (photocopy), typed interview transcripts (one with handwritten edits), pages from published articles (original and photocopies; also noting Shuggie Otis), typed draft of "The Johnny Otis Story," with handwritten edits, correspondence, and typed and handwritten drafts of other writings.
  - Art Pepper, undated (Box-folder 5/16)
    Photocopy of "The Megatape Sessions" song list, and typed drafts of liner notes (with handwritten edits). See box-folder 20/2 for oversized material.
  - Baden Powell, undated (Box-folder 5/17)
    Typed drafts of writings (with handwritten edits).
  - Jimmy Raney; 1979, undated (Box-folder 5/18)
    Typed drafts of writings (with handwritten edits), a published death notice, and handwritten notes.
  - Jimmy Reed, circa 1976-1993 (Box-folder 6/1)
    Typed draft of "Jimmy Reed notes - new introduction," plus original and photocopied pages from magazine(s).
  - Jimmy Rodgers, undated (Box-folder 6/2)
    Typed copies of Jimmie Rodgers and Hank Snow discographies.
  - Dr. Isaiah Ross, circa 1964-1966 (Box-folder 6/3)
    Typed drafts of writings (with handwritten edits), plus a handwritten letter to Welding from Dr. Ross.
  - Otis Rush, circa 1977 (Box-folder 6/4)
    Original clippings from magazines.
  - John Sellers, May 1965 (Box-folder 6/5)
    Original magazine clippings.
  - Shakey Jake, circa 1972 (Box-folder 6/6)
    Typed drafts of interview introduction and transcribed interview, plus a letter from Welding to "Bruce."
  - Robert Shaw, December 1966 (Box-folder 6/7)
    Original clipping from Jazz Beat magazine.
  - Don Schlitten, November 1977 (Box-folder 6/8)
    Two typed transcriptions of an interview; with handwritten edits.
  - Johnny Shines, circa 1970 (Box-folder 6/9)
    Typed sections of a transcribed interview, handwritten notes with doodles, a typed introduction to the interview, and original and photocopied pages from publications.
  - Frank Sinatra, circa 1987-1994 (Box-folders 6/10-11)
    Original and photocopied pages from publications, typed and handwritten lists of songs performed by Sinatra, handwritten notes, and one letter to Welding from John Ridgway.
  - Bessie Smith, circa 1967-1979 (Box-folder 6/12)
    Typed drafts of documents, plus original and photocopied pages from publications.
  - Clarence "Pinetop" Smith; 1939, undated (Box-folder 6/13)
    Draft typed version of article by Sharon Pease on Smith for Down Beat, plus copyright registration information for the article, a copy of Smith's death certificate, and related documents. The photos have been relocated to box-folder 22/19.
  - Otis Spann, 1970 (Box-folder 6/14)
    Two original clippings from publications.
  - Arthur "Big Boy" Spires, undated (Box-folder 6/15)
    Typed bio-discography of Spires by Welding.
  - Staple Singers, circa 1960s (Box-folder 7/1)
    Published materials about the Staple Singers, plus a one-page typed draft of introductory matter for an unidentified project.
  - Tampa Red, 1939 (Box-folder 7/2)
    A typed half-page of a passage on Tampa Red copied from Down Beat magazine; the issue was dated November 15, 1939.
  - Hound Dog Taylor; 1975-1982, undated (Box-folder 7/3)
    A two-page typed draft of a record review by Welding, a clipping from Guitar, dated August 1975, and a Nostalgia Book Club catalog.
  - Big Mama Thornton, October 1966; undated (Box-folder 7/4)
    Photocopy of a published article, typed draft of an article with handwritten edits, and photocopies of photos (the photos have been relocated to box-folder 23/2 ).
  - Henry Townsend, July 5, 1967; undated (Box-folder 7/5)
    Typed letter of correspondence, plus two versions of an interview (both with handwritten edits), and Townsend's business card.
  - Luther Tucker, undated (Box-folder 7/6)
    Original two-page article on Tucker, from an unidentified magazine.
  - Ike Turner, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Big Joe Turner, September 1965 (Box-folder 7/8)
    Photocopied draft of a typed text written about Joe Turner, a typed draft of another work on Turner (with some corrections), and an original clipping from a magazine.
  - Johnny Turner, October 1977 (Box-folder 7/9)
    Two typed drafts and possibly some other pages of an older draft (with corrections) of Welding's article Blues With a Feeling, a flyer for Jake Leg Records, and a magazine clipping about Turner.
  - Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson, May 8, 1975 (Box-folder 7/10)
    Clipping from a magazine.
  - Walter Vinson, March 9, 1962 (Box-folder 7/11)
    One-page copy of Blues News.
  - T-Bone Walker, circa 1965-1977 (Box-folder 7/12)
    Typed drafts of various writings on Walker (both originals and photocopies), original and photocopies clippings from magazines, a handwritten letter from a person (Jack?) at Down Beat to Pete, and a typed note.
  - Clara Ward, undated (Box-folder 7/13)
    Two typed drafts of an essay about Ward.
  - Gayle Wardlow; 1965-1966, undated (Box-folder 7/14)
    One handwritten letter and three typed letters from Wardlow to Welding, plus an original printed copy of OJL [Original Jazz Library] Supplement, no. 1 (1965).
  - Muddy Waters; 1959-1980, undated (Box-folders 7/15-16)
    A typed letter from Michael Cuscuna to Welding, a typed letter to "Art" from Welding, typed drafts of various writings (e.g., liner notes) about Waters; some with handwritten edits, and one with Welding's sketches on the back of various people, and several clippings (most original) from various magazines. See folder 20/3 for oversized material.
  - Pete Welding; 1960-1995, undated (Box-folder 7/17)
    Original and photocopied articles about Welding from various magazines, a flyer from Testament Records, a typed letter from Leonard Watkins, a typed letter from George Feltenstein to Welding, a copy of Welding's resume, and photocopies of photos relocated to box-folder 23/5.
  - Junior Wells; May 1975, undated (Box-folder 8/1)
    Two photocopied articles from magazines.
  - Peetie Wheatstraw, 1953 (Box-folder 8/2)
    Photocopied article by Paul Oliver from an unidentified publication.
  - Bukka White; 1971-1977, undated (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Robert Wilkins, undated (Box-folder 8/4)
    Original, typed interview transcription, typed proof with edits, and handwritten notes.
  - Big Joe Williams; 1964-1966, undated (Box-folder 8/5)
    Original, typed drafts of interview transcriptions (one with handwritten edits, an original, handwritten letter from Williams to Welding, and original clipping from a magazine.
  - Robert Pete Williams; 1968-1970, undated (Box-folder 8/6)